<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rails, | Code Worrier]]></title>
  <link href="http://code-worrier.com/blog/categories/rails-/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://code-worrier.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-04T21:06:19-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://code-worrier.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michael Hoffman]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[m@hof.fm]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Try out Routes in the Rails Console]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-worrier.com/blog/test-routes-in-rails-console/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-04T20:23:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-worrier.com/blog/test-routes-in-rails-console</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>How do you quickly check what path a certain route helper maps to?</p>

<p>One method I use a lot is to grep <code>rake routes</code>.
So, let's say I'm looking for a route that has to do with comment approval.
In that case, I might run <code>rake routes | grep approve</code>.
And there's my answer:</p>

<p><code>ruby
approve_comment POST  /comments/:id/approve(.:format)  {:action=&gt;"approve", :controller=&gt;"comments"}
</code></p>

<p>There's one problem with this, though: It's
  <a href="http://i.minus.com/iBKc6u9W2Zreb.gif" target="_blank">slooooow</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It's slow because running <code>rake routes</code> loads up your whole Rails environment.
If your workflow is anything like mine, though, chances are you've already have your environement loaded in another tab: the one where you have a Rails console running.
So in cases where you have some idea what the name of the route is, testing it  out in the console can save you time.
And, luckily, it couldn't be simpler.</p>

<p>In the Rails console, the variable <code>app</code> holds a session object on which you can call path and url helpers as instance methods.
So away we go:</p>

<p>``` ruby</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><p>app.approve_comment_path(Comment.last.id)
=> "/comments/138138/approve"
app.user_path(User.find_by_login("Michael Hoffman"))
=> "/users/784-michael-hoffman"
```</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>That's all there is to it.</p>

<p><em>(See <a href="code-worrier.com/blog/custom-slugs-in-rails/">this post</a> for my way of generating custom slugs like the one in that user path.)</em></p>

<p><em>(Searching around a bit, I think I originally got this tip from <a href="http://37signals.com/svn/posts/3176-three-quick-rails-console-tips" target="_bank">this wonderful post</a>. Read it to learn about other useful things you can accomplish with <code>app</code>.)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How do you prevent ActionMailer from spamming people in development?]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-worrier.com/blog/rails-intercept-emails-in-dev/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-18T19:09:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-worrier.com/blog/rails-intercept-emails-in-dev</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been working on a Rails app that contains lots of mailers with hard-coded recipients.
For instance, here's a mailer that we use to notify folks when someone asks an urgent question on our hotline:</p>

<p>```ruby hotline_mailer.rb
class HotlineMailer &lt; ActionMailer::Base</p>

<p>  default :from => "notifications@mywebapp.com"</p>

<p>  def notify_urgent_question(question)</p>

<pre><code>@question = question
send( :to =&gt; "urgent@mywebapp.com", 
      :subject =&gt; "Urgent: #{question.title}")
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  # Other mailer methods...</p>

<p>end
```</p>

<p>The email address "urgent@mywebapp.com" generates emails to many people.
We handle membership in Google apps.</p>

<p>Left to its own devices, this mailer will trigger an email to that list of people every time you hit the controller action that calls for it to be delivered.</p>

<p>That's bad news if you're just testing out the action in your development environment.
You have a group of people who are getting annoying emails for no reason, and you may not even be getting the emails yourself!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>We might consider using a constant in place of the email address, and initializing this constant differently in different environments.
However, this approach has two shortcomings:</p>

<ol>
<li>If we have more than one person working on the project, it's hard to choose which email address to use as the default for development.</li>
<li>We'll all have to remember to make a new constant every time we have a new email address that needs to be masked.</li>
</ol>


<p>Luckily, ActionMailer makes a better solution possible. Here's what you need to do:</p>

<p>```ruby lib/development_mail_interceptor.rb
class DevelopmentMailInterceptor</p>

<p>  def self.delivering_email(message)</p>

<pre><code>message.to = defined?(PERSONAL_EMAIL) ? PERSONAL_EMAIL : "default@mywebapp.com"
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end
```</p>

<p><code>ruby config/initializers/mailer_config.rb
require 'development_mail_interceptor'
ActionMailer::Base.register_interceptor(DevelopmentMailInterceptor) if  Rails.env.development?
</code></p>

<p><code>ruby config/initializers/personal_email.rb
PERSONAL_EMAIL = "personal@mywebapp.com"
</code></p>

<p>Lastly, you want to git ignore <code>config/initializers/personal_email.rb</code>, and tell your collaborators to create their own local version of the file.
(You want to git ignore it so that it can be customized per dev box.)</p>

<p>What does this all do?
When you call <code>#deliver</code> on an message, if the environment is development, the <code>to</code> option on the mailer is overridden with your personal address.
(In this example, it's "personal@mywebapp.com").
That's it!
We set up the default in the interceptor in case one of our collaborators doesn't get the message about creating <code>personal_email.rb</code>.
In that case, that person's dev mailer emails will be sent to the default you set in the interceptor class.
(In this example it's "default@mywebapp.com")</p>

<p>When I first struck upon this solution, I was worried that the interceptor would prevent me from seeing who would actually receive a given email if the code were running in production.
I needn't have worried.
The interceptor only affects the behavior of the <code>#deliver</code> method; the message object remains intact.
So, if you call</p>

<blockquote><p><code>HotlineMailer.notify_urgent_question(question)</code></p></blockquote>

<p>you'll find that object returned has the attribute <code>&lt;To: urgent@mywebapp.com&gt;</code>.
That's the address this email would go to if the interceptor did not interfere.
However, if you call</p>

<blockquote><p><code>HotlineMailer.notify_urgent_question(question).deliver</code>,</p></blockquote>

<p>the object returned has the attribute <code>&lt;To: personal@mywebapp.com&gt;</code> and sends the email to that address.</p>

<p>I think this is an effective solution, but it could be better.
Forcing developers to manually create files in order to properly use your repo is not ideal.
If you have an idea to improve this system, I'd love to hear about it in the comments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
